# James Tymann

# Overview

Experienced team lead and software engineer with a passion for solving novel and interesting problems. Excited to dissect problems, and find solutions that make products better. Strong web dev skills, with a focus on backend and server structure and architecture.

# Work Experience

### The Social Edge

2016 to 2017 — Fullstack Developer — New York, NY

The Social Edge is a startup who had found their place in the market with a series of prototypes. I was brought on to rearchitect their solutions so that they were modern, stable, and scalable.

#### Astrometrics

- · Arcitected a replacement to an existing tool that handles the processing, saving, and archiving of third party data and metrics.
- Built to scale so that the service can grow as the product grows, without redesigning the system
- Implemented real time data processing so data could be shown immediately on the product, whereas all data was delayed using the old system
- · Provided data pipelines so that more services could analyze the dataset effectively, and a synchronously
- Decreased data retrieval time so that larger sets of data can be analyzed.
- Allowed us integrate machine learning services into our stack
- Saved money by utilizing services that scale better, and for less money. Saving hundreds on monthly hosting costs.

#### Contempo

- Upgraded a legacy PHP application to a Node/REST api backend and a standalone React/AltJS frontend
- · Established continuous integration environments for easier environment management and software deploys
- · Successfully launched the tool with complete feature coverage, and enhancements to save employees and customers time.

#### Process Establishment

- · Worked with the engineering team to come up with a process that met the team's work styles and needs
- Implemented a version of scrum, that solved for the team's needs in terms of planning and development time
- Provided better team management, requirements elicitation, and communication to upper management as to what is being worked on

#### SQL Lessons

- The Social Edge's Sales and Media teams live and die by analyzing internal data and reports. The most important data is provided via regular reports and dashboard, however many teams craved more real time, or more in-depth data analysis.
- · Lead SQL fundamentals classes so that teams could learn to access data directly, and outside of the limitations of precompiled reports
- Teams used their new SQL knowledge to provide faster, more poignant updates to their teams. While other teams used this knowledge to analyze data to finer degrees, discovering new sales techniques.

## **Brand Networks**

2014 to 2016 — Product Architect — New York, NY 2013 to 2014 — Partner Engineer — New York, NY 2010 to 2013 — Senior Software Engineer — Rochester, NY

#### #Momento - Product Architect

- Conceptualized and implemented a brand new social media activation for events.
- Designed an event activation experience that tackled a variety of problems: slow or intermittent internet access, non-technical on-site contractors being able to assemble and troubleshoot the product, and being robust enough to handle frequent shipping.
- Made  $\frac{1}{4}$  of a million in revenue in the first quarter of launch

## Amex Open Forum - Lead Engineer

- Architected a new social media platform for small business owners.
- · Worked directly with the client to both create a new product to meet their needs, while simultaneously migrating a legacy product
- Successfully migrated and moved thousands of articles to a new theme, and format with little to no impact on existing users and admins
- · Built a new social community for small business owners to share information

#### American Express Offers - Lead Engineer

- · Worked directly with Facebook and American Express to implement a system that provided users with individually tailored offers and deals
- Implemented a joining of systems to create a new user experience
- Product was featured in a national tv ad

# Skills

Programming: Node / Javascript, HTML / CSS, C#, PHP, Java, Swift, CouchDB, MySQL, MSSQL Libraries and Frameworks: React, Flux, Angular, Bootstrap, jQuery, ASP.NET

 $Hosting\ and\ Devices:\ AWS,\ Rackspace,\ Heroku,\ iOS,\ Android,\ Windows,\ Linux$ 

# Education

BS in Software Engineering at Rochester Institute of Technology, Rochester, NY  $\,$